<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.2.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://cantandum.westminster.org.uk/programme-notes/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://cantandum.westminster.org.uk/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2025-07-19T10:37:57+00:00</updated><id>https://cantandum.westminster.org.uk/programme-notes/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Cantandum - London chamber choir | Programme</title><subtitle>Cantandum is a London-based chamber choir dedicated to performing a diverse repertoire of choral music, from Renaissance masterpieces to contemporary works. Join us for inspiring concerts, community events, and a celebration of vocal excellence.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Renaissance Treasures</title><link href="https://cantandum.westminster.org.uk/programme-notes/renaissance-treasures/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Renaissance Treasures" /><published>2024-03-20T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-03-20T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://cantandum.westminster.org.uk/programme-notes/renaissance-treasures</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://cantandum.westminster.org.uk/programme-notes/renaissance-treasures/"><![CDATA[<p>Lobo Versa est in luctum
Lassus Missa Bell’ Amfitrit altera
Byrd Ne irascaris Domine
Josquin Praeter rerum serium
White Lamentations a5</p>

<p>Alonso Lobo (1555-1617) was a Spanish composer of the late Renaissance, considered by Tomás Luis de Victoria as his equal. Lobo’s elegiac masterpiece Versa est in luctum was written in 1598 for the memorial service at Toledo Cathedral for Philip II of Spain. One of his most enduring works, it was published in his Liber primus missarum of 1602, headed ‘Ad exequias Philip. II Cathol. Regis Hisp.’. The text is an exquisite and evocative imagery of heavenly harps, organs and voices in songful mourning. Waves of entries roll over one another, drawing the ear into cycles of harmonic movement, before resolving redemptively in the major.</p>

<p>Orlande de Lassus (1532-1594) was a leading composer of the late Renaissance. Born in modern-day Belgium and working throughout Europe, he became one of the most prolific composers of his time. Around 60 masses have survived complete, and many of them are parody masses, using secular works as a melodic source.</p>

<p>The magnificent Missa Bell’ Amfitrit’ altera is based on a madrigal that has so far remained unidentified but may be Venetian, since Amphitrite was a sea-nymph.  It is a superb example of the composer’s polychoral style, which rather than being purely antiphonal prefers interplay between parts drawn from both choirs.  The Christe eleison and Benedictus reduce to the flowing counterpoint of four voices, heightening the impact of the return to eight voices, and the whole piece is in a shimmering major mode.</p>

<p>William Byrd (1539-1623) was the most noted and prolific English composer of his time.  He became Organist and Master of the Choristers at Lincoln Cathedral in 1563 before moving to the Chapel Royal in London in 1572. During the 1580s and 1590s Byrd’s Catholicism became the driving force for his music; he wrote and openly published motets and masses, almost certainly composed for small chapel gatherings.  The elaborate and penitential Ne irascaris, Domine, along with its seconda pars Civitas sancti tui, is one of Byrd’s masterpieces and one of his most forceful acts of protest against the persecution of English catholics. The setting is of verses from Isaiah 64.  The atmosphere is of quiet polyphonic contemplation, with the melody contained within the range of a fourth, before the stark homophony of ‘Sion deserta facta est’. The final phrase is a moving lament for Jerusalem – a metaphor for the catholic church in England – in which the poignant words ‘desolata est’ are heard over 50 times.</p>

<p>The magnificent, dark-hued Praeter rerum seriem, by Josquin (1450?-1521) takes the form of a succession of carefully worked motifs around a cantus firmus. For much of the piece the polyphony is presented antiphonally between the three upper voices, when the plainsong is in the soprano, and the three lower voices, when it is in the tenor. The second part of the motet is rather freer than the first, concealing the plainsong in a more consistently six-part texture, breaking into a lilting triple-time where the text makes final reference to the mystery of the Trinity, before returning to the duple time of ‘Mater ave’.</p>

<p>Robert White (1538-1574), arguably one the leading English composers of his time, was appointed organist and master of the choristers at Westminster Abbey in 1570. He and his wife and young family died in the plague only four years later.</p>

<p>The five-part Lamentations, consisting of two separate laments customarily sung together, are magnificent pieces of vocal architecture, with emotion in both halves drawn towards the concluding ‘Jerusalem, Jerusalem, convertere ad Dominum Deum tuum’.  The writing is restrained, reflecting the sombre nature of the texts of the prophet Jeremiah lamenting the downfall of Jerusalem.</p>

<p>The first four chapters of the Book of Lamentations are written as acrostics, with the first line of each verse corresponding to the 22 letters of the Hebrew alphabet, perhaps expressing a principle of completeness.  White sets verses 8-13 from the first book, following the convention of setting these letters (starting from the 8th, Heth) in poetically flowering music, rather like an illuminated capital letter at the outset of each verse.</p>

<p>It is one of several superb settings of that text composed during the 1560s, perhaps suggesting that not everybody was happy with the religious situation.  The Babylonians’ sacking of Jerusalem (the historical impetus for the Lamentations of Jeremiah) had become a metaphor for the plight of English Catholics over the ensuing decades.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A Floreat concert featuring treasures from the Renaissance period, showcasing the golden age of choral polyphony.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Your sweetest notes employ</title><link href="https://cantandum.westminster.org.uk/programme-notes/your-sweetest-notes-employ/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Your sweetest notes employ" /><published>2024-03-08T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-03-08T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://cantandum.westminster.org.uk/programme-notes/your-sweetest-notes-employ</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://cantandum.westminster.org.uk/programme-notes/your-sweetest-notes-employ/"><![CDATA[<p>Stanford Ye choirs of new Jerusalem
Stanford How beauteous are the feet
Mozart Great Mass in C minor, KV 427</p>

<p>The Anglo-Irish Sir Charles Villiers Stanford (1852-1924) was organist at Trinity College Cambridge and one of the founding professors of the Royal College of Music, where he taught composition. He was influenced by the classical principles of the music of Johannes Brahms, and counted amongst his pupils Holst and Vaughan Williams.</p>

<p>Ye choirs of New Jerusalem, an anthem for Eastertide, dates from 1910. The text is taken from the hymn by St Fulbert of Chartres, translated by Robert Campbell, on the theme of Christ as the deliverer of the prisoners from hell.  Stanford’s anthem alternates between two contrasting thematic ideas, one in the major mode in a lilting triple metre (‘Ye choirs of New Jerusalem’), the other in the minor and in quadruple metre (‘Devouring depths of hell their prey’). The triple metre returns for the splendid final ‘Alleluia’.</p>

<p>This fine setting of How beauteous are their feet takes its text from four verses of Isaac Watts’s hymn. Stanford contrives a sophisticated variation form based on the opening melodic idea, with the polyphonic treatment of each repetition subtly varied.  In the fourth verse – ‘The Lord makes bare his arm’ – the tonic minor brings with it  a moment of gravitas, which is soon dispelled by the uplifting return of the major mode.</p>

<p>The monumental Mass in C minor, by Wolfgang Amadeus Mozart (1756-1791), is one of his greatest works.  Like his Requiem, it is magnificent but incomplete, in concept perhaps echoing something of the extraordinary proportions of Bach’s Mass in B minor.</p>

<p>Mozart began work on this Great Mass in the summer of 1782, around the time of his marriage to Constanze Weber and at a time when he was acquainting himself with Handel’s oratorios and Bach’s great fugues.  It was premiered in Salzburg in October 1783, presumably in a partially complete form, with Constanze as a soprano soloist.  The autograph manuscript contains the Kyrie and Gloria, the only movements that are fully complete, the first two verses of the Credo in short score, and a wind band score of the Sanctus which has survived only as a copyist’s manuscript.  The end of the Credo and the entire Agnus Dei are missing.  Despite all this, several convincing reconstructions have enabled the work to be performed today.</p>

<p>The work is sometimes described as a cantata mass, with alternating movements for four- and eight-part chorus, ensemble and soloists.  The work opens with an exquisite Kyrie, for soprano soloist and choir, which is followed by a rousing choral Gloria, embodying the pomp and solemnity associated with Salzburg tradition.  An Italianate coloratura Laudamus te is next. Domine Deus is a glorious pyrotechnical duet for two sopranos, after which there is a powerful 8-part Qui tollis, an Italianate trio Quoniam tu solus sanctus and a magnificently fugal Cum sancto spiritu.  The two movements of the creed are sharply contrasting – a lively Credo followed by an ethereal soprano aria Et incarnatus.  The 8-part Sanctus contains a splendidly fugal Osanna, which is partly repeated after an extended Benedictus, a serious exercise in worked counterpoint for four soloists.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A concert celebrating the beauty of sacred music with works that employ the sweetest notes of choral tradition.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://cantandum.westminster.org.uk/assets/images/476398645_1298944694632615_307762129408279843_n.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://cantandum.westminster.org.uk/assets/images/476398645_1298944694632615_307762129408279843_n.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Byrd’s the Word</title><link href="https://cantandum.westminster.org.uk/programme-notes/byrds-the-word/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Byrd’s the Word" /><published>2023-12-07T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-12-07T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://cantandum.westminster.org.uk/programme-notes/byrds-the-word</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://cantandum.westminster.org.uk/programme-notes/byrds-the-word/"><![CDATA[<p>Josquin   Praeter rerum serium
Tallis   Videte miraculum
Byrd   Laudibus in sanctis
Byrd   Kyrie from Mass for four voices
Byrd   Vigilate
Byrd   Sanctus and Benedictus from Mass for four voices
Byrd   O quam gloriosum
Byrd   Agnus Dei from Mass for four voices
Bach   Lobet den Herrn
Janequin   Le chant des oyseaux
Passereau   Il est bel et bon</p>

<p>The magnificent Praeter rerum seriem, by Josquin (1450?-1521) takes the form of a succession of carefully worked motifs around the cantus firmus on which it is based. For much of the piece the polyphony is presented antiphonally between the three upper voices, when the chant is in the soprano, and the three lower voices, when it is in the tenor. The second part of the motet is rather freer than the first, concealing the plainchant in what has become a more consistently six-part texture, breaking into triple-time where the text makes final reference to the mystery of the Trinity, before returning to the duple time of ‘Mater ave’.</p>

<p>Videte miraculum is the Responsory at Candlemas. The chant on which Tallis (1505-1585) bases his polyphony comprises several sections, the full choir alternating with solo cantor. He leaves the solo sections as unadorned chant, implanting the choral sections of chant in a six-voice polyphonic texture. Listen for the opening point of imitation on ‘miraculum’—a dissonance, repeated at regular intervals by each entering voice to hypnotic effect, and for fleeting glimpses of major at ‘ad matrem’.</p>

<p>William Byrd (1539-1623), a pupil of Tallis, was the most prodigiously talented and prolific English composer of his time.  His earliest-known employment was as Organist and Master of the Choristers at Lincoln Cathedral.  In 1572 he took up a position at the Chapel Royal in London.  During the 1580s and 1590s Byrd’s Catholicism became the driving force for his music; he wrote and openly published motets and masses, almost certainly composed for small chapel gatherings.  Daringly, he openly published this music; unsurprisingly, it is deeply expressive.</p>

<p>The athletically ebullient Laudibus in sanctis, a paraphrase in Latin elegiac verse of Psalm 150, comes from his Cantiones Sacrae of 1591. It is full of madrigalianisms, involving rhythmic rhetoric, syncopation, melodic representations of the words, and a wonderful section in triple time as the poet dances before God.</p>

<p>The Mass for Four Voices, dating from 1592 or 1593, is the first and perhaps most personal of his three masses.  It retains some techniques from the distant past, such as blurring the boundaries between the tenor and alto parts, yet there are moments of intensity as well.  A central tenet of Elizabethan catholicism was its historical legitimacy, and Byrd makes an explicit homage in referencing, especially in the Sanctus, the pre-Reformation composer John Taverner’s ‘Mean’ Mass.  A plaintive Kyrie and a delicate Sanctus and Benedictus look towards an exquisite Agnus Dei.</p>

<p>Vigilate is notable for its madrigalian characteristics, such as sudden changes in declamatory style, the highlighting of individual words and short phrases, and overt illustrations of textual ideas in the music. The text, from Mark 13: 35–37, is presented from the perspective of Christ, warning his disciples of their inevitable deaths, which could come suddenly and without warning. This message might be read as a warning to English Catholics about the potential mortal danger from civil authorities, or as a metaphor about God coming suddenly in judgment.</p>

<p>O quam gloriosum and its second part, Benedictio et claritas are motets for the Feast of All Saints.  The first is derived from the Magnificat antiphon ‘O how glorious is the kingdom’, and the second from the service of None, ‘Blessing and glory and wisdom and thanksgiving and honour and power and might be unto our God for ever and ever’.  A choir of saints radiates assurance, gleaming with lucid major triads and an even, suffused light, and shows Byrd working at the height of his inspiration.</p>

<p>Lobet den Herrn, by J.S. Bach (1685-1750) is usually considered a motet but its independent continuo part leads some to believe that it may stem from an otherwise lost cantata. Its attribution to Bach is questionable. The text comes from Psalm 117:1-2. The opening text is a fugue starting with the sopranos and cascading its way down to the basses. Billowing roulades on the word ‘preiset ihn’ (praise Him) are followed by supple homophony, giving way to a gracious fugal passage. An infectious, dancing Alleluia concludes the motet.</p>

<p>Le chant des oyseaux is a chanson by Janequin (1485-1558), with birdsong brilliantly portrayed in fast rhythmic figures.  In its first part, the singers bid sleepy hearts awaken, for the god of love is calling on the first of May, and the birds will amaze you. The following three parts sequentially introduce the royal song thrush and blackbird, the nightingale, and the cuckoo, shifting between brief French descriptors and nonsense syllables and music that emulate each bird’s chirping song. The text contains fleeting references to drinking, adultery, and other unholy behaviour.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A Floreat concert celebrating the genius of William Byrd, one of England's greatest composers.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://cantandum.westminster.org.uk/assets/images/476004915_1296504828209935_4908642338181519064_n.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://cantandum.westminster.org.uk/assets/images/476004915_1296504828209935_4908642338181519064_n.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">From darkness to light</title><link href="https://cantandum.westminster.org.uk/programme-notes/from-darkness-to-light/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="From darkness to light" /><published>2023-11-30T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-11-30T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://cantandum.westminster.org.uk/programme-notes/from-darkness-to-light</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://cantandum.westminster.org.uk/programme-notes/from-darkness-to-light/"><![CDATA[<p>Ledger   Jesus Christ the Apple Tree
Buxtehude   Magnificat
Ledger   Adam lay y bounden
Wilbye   Draw on, sweet night
East   Hence stars, too dim of light
Rutter   Dormi, Jesu
Davies   O little town of Bethlehem
Poulenc   Videntes stellam
Handl   Ab Oriente venerunt magi
Holst   Nunc dimittis
Macmillan   O radiant dawn
Wood   O thou the central orb
Handel   Let the bright seraphim; Let their celestial concerts all unite</p>

<p>Philip Ledger (1937-2012) was Director of Music of King’s College, Cambridge between 1974 and 1982, and a noted choral composer. Jesus Christ the Apple Tree is an 18th-century poem that first appeared in London’s Spiritual Magazine in August 1761. The text to Adam lay y bounden is thought to date from around 1400 and is a macaronic setting of the story of the Fall of Man, Adam being released from limbo by the death of Christ four thousand years later.  Ledger’s settings are refreshingly unostentatious in their simplicity and craftsmanship, demonstrating simple yet memorable melody and harmony in uncomplicated verse structures.</p>

<p>Dietrich Buxtehude (1637- 1707), organist at the Marienkirche at Lübeck, is unlikely to be the composer of this Magnificat, but the piece has been so long associated with him that the attribution has remained.  It is a delightful piece which obtains striking results by way of enduring lilting melodies, simple harmonies, frequent hemiolas and a clear sectional structure.</p>

<p>John Wilbye (1574-1638) was a prolific composer of English madrigals, with a style characterized by delicate voice-writing, acute sensitivity to text, a seriousness of approach and a subtlety of musical ideas.  Draw on, sweet night, possibly the greatest of all the English madrigals, displays a wistful melancholy and subtle alternation of major and minor modes.  Michael East (1580-1648) was a member of the choir of Ely Cathedral before moving to Lichfield as a lay clerk and choirmaster.  Hence stars, too dim of light is from ‘The Triumphs of Oriana’, a collection of madrigals by 23 composers, commissioned by Thomas Morley in honour of an ageing Queen Elizabeth and painting her as an eternally bountiful queen of a pastoral Arcadia.  After a brief homophonic statement there follow several lines of nimble imitation, particularly effective on the wordy ‘you dazzle but the sight, you teach to grope by night’.</p>

<p>John Rutter (1945- ) is an English choral composer, especially renowned for his effective and enduring settings of many Christmas carols.  Dormi Jesu sets an anonymous Latin text with its translation by Samuel Taylor Coleridge and is a tender lullaby.  It is a classic example of his style, with its final blues-esque chord being an notable touch.  O Little Town of Bethlehem is best known in its setting to the English folk melody, ‘The ploughboy’s dream’, as arranged by Vaughan Williams, but this 1913 version by Henry Walford Davies (1869-1941) has become a much-loved alternative. It begins with a solo soprano recitative, of text from the angel’s message to the shepherds in the Gospel of Luke, before moving into four hauntingly beautiful verses, the first of which is also a solo.</p>

<p>Francis Poulenc (1899-1963) is one of the supreme composers of French religious music, with a simple and direct style.  His choral music is unusually taxing, with strange key changes and awkward intervals all making for startlingly beautiful textures.  Despite its brevity, Videntes stellam, from Quatre motets pour le temps de Nöel, is an exquisite example of the composer at the height of his choral brilliance, brimming with freshness and clarity.  Ab oriente venerunt magi, by the Bohemian composer Jacob Handl (1550-1591), dates from 1586 and is a setting of the Magnificat Antiphon for Epiphany, telling the story of the Wise Men and their gifts of ‘aurum, thus et myrrham’.  It starts with lovely word-painting depicting the journey to Bethlehem and ends with a dance-like Alleluia.  The 8-part unaccompanied Nunc dimittis by Gustav Holst (1874-1934) was first performed liturgically on Easter Sunday 1915 and thereafter remained in manuscript form until 1979 when a published edition appeared, revised by the composer’s daughter Imogen.  Holst’s esteem of Byrd and Palestrina is especially evident in the modal and antiphonal writing of this glorious piece.</p>

<p>O Radiant Dawn is the antiphon for 21 December. The 2007 setting by James Macmillan (1959-) depicts a fervent longing for Christ, with suspensions and dynamic crescendos emphasising the increasing desperation of the people and the final resolution from dissonance to consonance maybe a representation of the conflicts resolved by Jesus’ coming.  The Irish composer Charles Wood (1886-1926) wrote a considerable amount of church music, mostly towards the end of his life.  O Thou, the central orb is skilfully crafted and a joy to sing. The ‘central orb’ is Jesus, bringing to us God’s eternal light; it also symbolises kingship and the piece is often sung at royal occasions.</p>

<p>Let the celestial concerts all unite is the jubilant finale to the oratorio Samson, by G.F. Handel (1685-1759).  The largest of his biblical oratorios, written shortly after Messiah, it was a triumphant success, not least because of the inspired last-minute addition of a dazzling soprano aria, Let the bright seraphim, composed for the renowned Italian singer Christina Avoglio who happened to be in London that season and was willing to make a cameo appearance in Handel’s new oratorio.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A concert exploring the journey from darkness to light through sacred choral music.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://cantandum.westminster.org.uk/assets/images/476099596_1296497311544020_6095055138450864273_n.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://cantandum.westminster.org.uk/assets/images/476099596_1296497311544020_6095055138450864273_n.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">And music shall untune the sky - Celebratory Odes by Handel and Purcell</title><link href="https://cantandum.westminster.org.uk/programme-notes/and-music-shall-untune-the-sky/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="And music shall untune the sky - Celebratory Odes by Handel and Purcell" /><published>2023-06-09T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-06-09T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://cantandum.westminster.org.uk/programme-notes/and-music-shall-untune-the-sky</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://cantandum.westminster.org.uk/programme-notes/and-music-shall-untune-the-sky/"><![CDATA[]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A garden concert featuring celebratory odes by Handel and Purcell, celebrating the power of music.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Carole magnus eras – Music for a Monarch</title><link href="https://cantandum.westminster.org.uk/programme-notes/carole-magnus-eras/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Carole magnus eras – Music for a Monarch" /><published>2023-05-11T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-05-11T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://cantandum.westminster.org.uk/programme-notes/carole-magnus-eras</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://cantandum.westminster.org.uk/programme-notes/carole-magnus-eras/"><![CDATA[<p>No Details in the Wayback machine.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A Floreat concert featuring music written for and in celebration of monarchs throughout history.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://cantandum.westminster.org.uk/assets/images/472694161_1276806933513058_7714879660423850118_n.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://cantandum.westminster.org.uk/assets/images/472694161_1276806933513058_7714879660423850118_n.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Haydn and Stanford</title><link href="https://cantandum.westminster.org.uk/programme-notes/haydn-and-stanford/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Haydn and Stanford" /><published>2023-03-09T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-03-09T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://cantandum.westminster.org.uk/programme-notes/haydn-and-stanford</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://cantandum.westminster.org.uk/programme-notes/haydn-and-stanford/"><![CDATA[<p>Haydn         Te Deum no. 2 in C
Stanford    Songs of the Fleet
Haydn        Nelson Mass</p>

<p>Franz Josef Haydn (1732-1809) was in his time the most celebrated composer in Europe, admired and revered by the public and by his peers. His works are characterised by a joyous exuberance, creative invention, classical elegance and intellectual power.</p>

<p>He composed two settings of the Te Deum, both in C major with the second being the more substantial of the two.  It was written in autumn 1799, at the suggestion of the Empress Maria Theresa, and received its premiere the following year in the presence of Lord Nelson.  It is a magnificent choral drama in three parts, with two lengthy Allegro passages in C major surrounding a central, prayerfully contemplative and harmonically chromatic Adagio in C minor.  The striking opening Allegro incorporates plainchant whilst the final ebullient section concludes with a magnificent double fugue at ‘In te Domine speravi’ with a syncopated coda.</p>

<p>In 1795 Haydn’s employer Prince Nikolaus Esterhazy commissioned him to compose a new setting of the mass each year to mark the name-day of his wife, Princess Maria. The Nelson Mass of 1798, described by Robbins Landon as ‘arguably Haydn’s greatest single composition’, is the third and most celebrated of these last masses.</p>

<p>In 1800 Nelson, heralded as the saviour of Europe since his victory over Napoleon’s fleet at the Battle of the Nile, visited Prince Nikolaus Esterhazy at Eisenstadt, where he and Sir William and Lady Emma Hamilton met Haydn. It was here that the Te Deum, along with the Mass in D minor, were performed in Nelson’s honour.  It used to be assumed that the mass had been inspired by Nelson’s victory, but news of the battle did not reach Eisenstadt until two weeks after the work was completed. Whatever the reason, after his visit it became known as the Nelson Mass. Haydn later catalogued it as Missa in Angustiis (Mass in Troubled Times), a clear reference to the Napoleonic threat.</p>

<p>The dramatic Kyrie eleison opens in D minor. At Christe eleison the music moves to a brighter F major and the first of a series of virtuosic soprano solos is heard. Unsurprisingly, the Gloria reveals Haydn at his most cheerful, recalling the magnificent world of The Creation, first performed a few months earlier. The bass solo, Qui tollis peccata mundi, is a clear reference to Mozart’s Requiem, and perhaps intended as a tribute to Haydn’s admired colleague. After this slower section a soprano solo brings us back to the key of D for Quoniam tu solus, and the movement ends with a spirited fugue.  The Credo begins with a canon between pairs of voices in strict imitation at the fifth, apt for a strong declaration of faith.  The exquisite Et incarnatus est leads to an intense Crucifixus. The following Et resurrexit bursts into life with explosive energy, with a remarkable soprano solo at Et vitam venturi.  The chorus ‘speaks’ a portion of its lengthy text, declaiming on one repeated note, although here Haydn, who set his mass texts from memory, has apparently inadvertently omitted the words ‘qui ex Patre Filioque procedit’.</p>

<p>After the Sanctus comes the Benedictus, a movement of exceptional emotional and dramatic intensity. Here Haydn returns to the dark D minor tones heard in the Kyrie, with a series of exchanges between soloists and chorus culminating in a climax looking ahead, perhaps, to Beethoven. The Agnus Dei, sung by soloists only, is followed by an extended Dona nobis pacem which, in contrast to the usual supplicatory prayer, is almost operatic in style, typical of Haydn at his most exuberant.</p>

<p>Songs of the Fleet, Op 117, by Charles Villiers Stanford (1852-1924), are written for solo baritone, chorus, and orchestra and date from 1910.  They were originally intended for the Jubilee Congress of Naval Architects to be held that year, but the death of Edward VII in May postponed the Congress until 1911; Stanford opted instead to unveil the work at the 1910 Leeds Festival, where it was triumphantly received.</p>

<p>There are five movements in total, of which we are singing three.  The first, the gloriously assured ‘Sailing at Dawn’, evokes a vast armada heading out of port as morning breaks.  Subtle harmonic touches underpin a memorable melodic line, where a baritone verse is answered by the chorus; both join together in the refrain (‘lead the line’), in which they remember the ‘souls of all the seadogs’ who went before.  The third movement, ‘The Middle Watch’, with its tonal shifts between G minor and G major, evokes a dusky mystery and sense of awe, an atmospheric portrayal of sailing at night and of looking ahead ‘til ye find life and the land of the morn’.  Music and text take a lighter turn in the fourth movement, ‘The Little Admiral’, a jaunty tribute to the enduring legacy of Horatio Nelson.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A concert featuring the contrasting yet complementary works of Joseph Haydn and Charles Villiers Stanford.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://cantandum.westminster.org.uk/assets/images/502972718_10234540306661917_3955130635025992115_n.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://cantandum.westminster.org.uk/assets/images/502972718_10234540306661917_3955130635025992115_n.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">From the realms of glory</title><link href="https://cantandum.westminster.org.uk/programme-notes/from-the-realms-of-glory/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="From the realms of glory" /><published>2022-12-01T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-12-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://cantandum.westminster.org.uk/programme-notes/from-the-realms-of-glory</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://cantandum.westminster.org.uk/programme-notes/from-the-realms-of-glory/"><![CDATA[<p>Rutter Angels carol
Durante Magnificat
Ledger The voice of the Angel Gabriel
Philips Gabriel Angelus
Palestrina Stetit angelus
Dering Factum est silencium
Ledger Angels from the realms of glory
Pearsall In dulci jubilo
Harris Faire is the heaven
Bairstow Let all mortal flesh keep silence
Vaughan Williams Te Deum in G
St Matthew’s Westminster</p>

<p>Tonight’s concert is on the theme on angels, not all of them Christmas ones. What you will hear this evening is music that is about, directly or indirectly, or has been inspired by, these timelessly enduring beings.</p>

<p>The name of John Rutter (b 1945) is almost synonymous with Christmas.  His work is characterised by an infectious melodic invention and consummate craftsmanship.  The delightful Angels’ Carol was written, to the composer’s own text, as a duet for the winners of the 1980 ‘choirboy and choirgirl of the year’ competition and was later arranged for SATB choir.</p>

<p>The joyous Magnificat by Francesco Durante (1684-1755) was for many years thought to be by his pupil Pergolesi.  The text is from the Gospel of Luke, where Mary, recently visited by the angel Gabriel, declares to her cousin Elizabeth the greatness of, and her delight in finding, God.  Durante composed two settings of the text, the B flat major one we hear tonight being in 4 parts.  It consists of six movements, with the counterpoint in the first built around the eighth psalm tone cantus firmus. In each successive movement, overlapping, imitative polyphony is used in concordance with the opening subject and is then woven throughout the entire movement using text, tempo and vocal colour to give it its own particular character. A short duet from soprano and alto (‘and his mercy is on them that fear him’) leads into an energetic scattering of the proud.  This is followed by a strongly fugal Deposuit, and expressive tenor and bass Suscepit Israel, a Sicut locutus est that is a recapitulation of the opening chorus, and a splendid Gloria.</p>

<p>Philip Ledger (1937-2012) was  Director of Music at King’s College Cambridge from 1974 to 1982.  The voice of the Angel Gabriel is one of his first compositions and alternates a haunting minor melody in the unaccompanied verses with a quietly affirmative organ-accompanied refrain in the relative major.  Angels from the realms of glory is a 4-part choral version of the much-loved hymn, part-unaccompanied and part with organ.</p>

<p>Peter Philips (1560-1628) enjoyed great fame in his lifetime. A prominent Catholic, he left England for Rome and later travelled across Europe for a few years before settling in Antwerp.  A prolific composer of motets and madrigals, he seemed to have been a serious, almost austere figure.  The 5-part Gabriel Angelus tells of Gabriel’s visit to Zachariah, announcing that he will soon have a son, John (the Baptist), who ‘vinum et ficeram non bibet’ (will not consume wine or strong drink).  It is in the format ABCBD, where D is the final alleluia; in other words, section B ʻet multi in nativitate eius gaudebuntʼ is repeated in such a way that the second time it goes straight into the alleluias, producing an effect of energy and momentum.</p>

<p>The text for the 5-part Stetit angelus, by Giovanni Pierluigi da Palestrina (1525-1594), who along with Victoria and Lassus was possibly the greatest composer of his time, is from Revelation 8:3-4 ‘An Angel stood near the altar of the temple, having a golden censer in his hand’. The motet is associated with the feastday of the archangel Michael and is also the first part of another, Inconspectu angelorum, for the archangel Raphael. Richard Dering (1580-1630) converted to Catholicism while visiting Rome in 1612 and later went into exile in the Spanish Netherlands. Factum est silentium, to a text from the Book of Revelation, depicts the battle between the Archangel Michael and a dragon, an allegory of the devil. It is declamatory, dramatic and madrigalean in style, with considerable variation of note durations, vividly contrasting textures and insistent, stylised rhythm.</p>

<p>In dulci jubilo is said to have been taught to the German mystic Hermann Seusse by angels. The text is macaronic, a mixture of medieval German and Latin.  Robert de Pearsall’s 1837 translation retains the Latin but substitutes English for German; a looser (and much-criticised) English version is better-known as Good Christian men, rejoice. The carol is best known in Reginald Jacques’ arrangement for Carols for Choirs, but what we hear tonight is closer to Pearsall’s own, retaining the original German and with more clearly-defined solo lines.</p>

<p>William Harris’s 1925 masterpiece Faire is the Heaven is one of the best-loved works in the Anglican repertoire. At various points in his career, Harris held appointments in London, Lichfield and Oxford and was for nearly thirty years Director of Music at St George’s Chapel, Windsor. Faire is the heaven is set in D flat major for double choir without accompaniment. The words are taken from Edmund Spenser’s An Hymn of Heavenly Beauty, first published in 1596. Harris selected lines from three stanzas of a poem over forty stanzas in length. The editing is subtle—so much so that a casual reader might not realize lines have been omitted—and a structure is created that lends itself to ternary treatment: Spenser’s ‘cherubins’ and ‘seraphins’ are assigned a faster section in the middle, and Harris engineers a memorable return to the home key for the final section of the anthem.  Edgar Bainton’s Let all mortal flesh keep silence also dates from 1925. It achieves its mysterious effect at the outset with tenor and bass in octaves, followed by upper voices only at the words ‘and lift itself above all earthly thought.’ This high-pitched texture returns as the words ‘the Cherubim with many eyes’ chime out with a short, arpeggiated ostinato-figure in the bass part. The final dramatic alleluias lead to a restatement of the opening material with a dark choral accompaniment.</p>

<p>The Te Deum in G by Ralph Vaughan Williams (1872-1958) was written in 1928. Commissioned for the enthronement of Cosmo Lang as Archbishop of Canterbury on 4 December, it rolls with confidence from the outset, a strong declamatory unison leading to an antiphonal representation of the angelic chorus before the opening material is transformed into a prayerful, supplicatory ending.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A Christmas concert celebrating the birth of Christ with music from the realms of glory.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://cantandum.westminster.org.uk/assets/images/470872029_1263052874888464_4122035590150326710_n.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://cantandum.westminster.org.uk/assets/images/470872029_1263052874888464_4122035590150326710_n.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Advent calendar</title><link href="https://cantandum.westminster.org.uk/programme-notes/advent-calendar/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Advent calendar" /><published>2022-11-24T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-11-24T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://cantandum.westminster.org.uk/programme-notes/advent-calendar</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://cantandum.westminster.org.uk/programme-notes/advent-calendar/"><![CDATA[<p>Ledger Advent Calendar
Gibbons This is the record of John
Guerrero Canite tuba
Byrd Vigilate
Bach, J.S. Komm Jesu, komm
Lloyd Adam our father
Praetorius, H. Magnificat quinti toni, with Christmas interpolations
Victoria O magnum mysterium
Bach, J.S. Der Geist hilft
St Stephen’s, Rochester Row
FLOREAT
Gilly French, Helen Prentice, Helena Bickley-Percival, Catharine Robertson
Jonathan Bull, Manvinder Rattan, Iain Butler, Robert Harvey Wood, Willow Northeald
with Dewi Rees organ</p>

<p>Philip Ledger (1937-2012) was Director of Music at King’s College, Cambridge and Principal of the Royal Scottish Academy of Music and Drama.  The 8-part Advent Calendar, to a text by Rowan Williams, Archbishop of Canterbury, and written in memory of George Guest, exudes the composer’s style of sensitive and reverent word-setting.  The moving poem is coloured with imagery, with ‘red December’ richly scored for divided tenors and basses and ascending upper voices conveying an image of the ‘star-snowed fields of sky’.  The music becomes dissonant, with augmented chords and whole-tone passages conform with textual expressions of a more threatening darkness, before arriving at a quiet, peaceful ending, emphasising the Christmas message that ‘He will come like child’.   Richard Lloyd (1933-2021) was organist at Hereford and Durham cathedrals. His distinctive choral music is accessible and beautifully crafted and stands out as some of the most rewarding of its time.  Adam our Father is a setting of a 15th-centry text about the fall of Adam and prophecies of a redeeming Christ child.  It has a stunningly haunting simplicity that endures in the heart.</p>

<p>Orlando Gibbons (1583-1625) was one of the most important English figures of the early 17th century.  He became a Gentleman of the Chapel Royal around 1603 and organist of Westminster Abbey in 1623.  A master of serious polyphonic music, his verse anthems show contrapuntal and vitality.  His verse anthems are amongst the finest of the genre: This is the Record of John shows a simple alternation of solo voice and five-part chorus, in three sections, with a superb declamatory solo line imitated each time by the chorus.  William Byrd (1539/40-1623) was the finest English composer of his age. During the 1580s and 1590s Byrd’s Catholicism became the driving force for his music; he wrote and openly published motets and masses, almost certainly composed for small chapel gatherings.  Vigilate is notable for its madrigalian characteristics, such as sudden changes in declamatory style, the highlighting of individual words and short phrases, and overt illustrations of textual ideas in the music. The text, from Mark 13: 35–37, is presented from the perspective of Christ, warning his disciples of their inevitable deaths, which could come suddenly and without warning. This message might be read as a warning to English Catholics about the potential mortal danger from civil authorities, or as a metaphor about God coming suddenly in judgment.</p>

<p>Francisco Guerrero (1528-1599) was born in Seville, where he was known for his early proficiency on several instruments and became maestro de capilla at the city’s cathedral. His Canite tuba in Sion was published in 1570; it uses the four voice-parts to imitate trumpets, conveying the urgency in the Advent responsory. The text is from Joel 2:1 and Isaiah 11:4 ‘Blow up the trumpet in Sion, for the day of God is near at hand’.  There is a clear harmonic impulse and the voices move smoothly and effortlessly.  The second part, Rorate Caeli (Drop down, ye heavens) is characterised by glorious word-painting, for example with the skies pouring down righteousness (nubes pluant justum) and the earth opening (aperiatur terra).  Tomas Luis da Victoria (1548-1611) was the greatest Spanish Renaissance composer and one of the leading figures of church music in the Europe of his day. The exquisite O magnum mysterium is one of his best-known works and was written when the composer was only 24. The text refers to the ‘great mystery’ and ‘wonderful sacrament’ of animals seeing the new-born Lord.</p>

<p>Joseph, lieber Joseph mein and In dulci iubilo are two of the best known of all ecclesiastical medieval tunes. Both carols are in compound duple time, and macaronic in that they use a mixture of German and Latin words. The German composer Hieronymous Praetorius (1560-1629) sets both pieces for eight voices, with Joseph, lieber Joseph mein for two contrasting four-voice choirs. The high point occurs where the top voice soars to the upper limit of its range with the clearly audible ‘Hodie apparuit’ in a majestic statement of the Christmas miracle. In dulci iubilo, for an 8-voice choir, is more athletic in its presentation of the text, with ebullient syncopations and directed suspensions propelling the music forward. Both carols fit perfectly into the monumental Magnificat quinti toni. Word-painting is evident throughout. The music rejoices, is holy, is powerful, scatters, and sends empty away as the text requires. Abraham is afforded unique respect through the use of resonant chords which allow the listener to connect directly with the Old Testament. The symphonic Gloria has all the voices sounding together to create a climax of extraordinary power and finality.</p>

<p>The music of Johann Sebastian Bach (1685-1750) is revered for its technical command, artistic beauty and intellectual depth.  Komm Jesu, komm, the fifth of his six motets, dates from around 1723-34 and is a setting of a funeral poem written by Paul Thymich (d. 1684).  The setting is for SATB double choir.  The opening section, in moderate triple metre, is the darkest.  Descending lines and angular counterpoint predominate, accentuating the hardships of life. It is remarkable for its word-painting, notably at ‘Der saure Weg’ (the bitter way), where the bitterness of life is emphasised with a downward leap of a diminished seventh in every voice, perhaps implying that no-one is exempt from earthly trials. The mood shifts to a more hopeful sentiment which, in turn, moves into a stately expression of faith; the words ‘You are the right way, the truth and the life’ are set as a dance in 6/8 for alternating choirs, moving through an interval of a fifth each time and culminating in a true eight-voice polyphony. With ecstatic confidence, a stately four-part chorale concludes the motet with the words ‘My spirit…shall soar with its creator’.   The eight-part Der Geist hilft was written for the funeral of J H Ernesti, Rector of St Thomas’s School, on 24 October 1729. The text combines scripture with contemporary devotional poetry: the main body is taken from Paul’s Epistle to the Romans while the words of the concluding chorale are by Martin Luther. Structurally, the motet unfolds as a sequence of continuous, loosely linked sections that are differentiated both musically and textually. The opening evocation of the Holy Ghost soars aloft in swirling semiquavers. A more sedate section ensues as the singers contemplate the Spirit’s prayerful intercession. After a brief cadential pause, Bach abruptly switches to duple meter at the words ‘sondern der Geist selbst’ with breathless syncopations and sighing figures painting the words ‘unaussprechlichem Seufzen’. The motet culminates in a vigorous fugue followed by a four-part chorale invoking the ‘holy fire’ of faith that strengthens us to press onward to God ‘through death and life.’</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A Floreat concert celebrating the Advent season with music marking the approach of Christmas.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://cantandum.westminster.org.uk/assets/images/496268169_10234303629785143_6640845216529323596_n.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://cantandum.westminster.org.uk/assets/images/496268169_10234303629785143_6640845216529323596_n.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">The flower of the field</title><link href="https://cantandum.westminster.org.uk/programme-notes/the-flower-of-the-field/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The flower of the field" /><published>2022-06-17T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-06-17T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://cantandum.westminster.org.uk/programme-notes/the-flower-of-the-field</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://cantandum.westminster.org.uk/programme-notes/the-flower-of-the-field/"><![CDATA[<p>Music for singing outdoors</p>

<p>Bennett – All creatures now
Padilla – Kyrie and Gloria from Missa Ego flos campi
Mendelssohn – Sechs Lieder, im Freien su zingen
Padilla – Credo from Missa Ego flos campi
Kodaly – Matra Pictures
Padilla – Sanctus and Benedictus from Missa Ego flos campi
Byrd – This sweet and merry month of May
Padilla – Agnus Dei from Missa Ego flos campi</p>

<p>Missa Ego flos campi (I am the flower of the field) by the Spanish-Mexican composer Juan Gutiérrez de Padilla (1590-1664) is a parody mass tinged with evangelical outbursts and touched by secular dance music. It is a remarkable and joyous double-choir setting that has elements of flowing polyphony from Old Spain combined with lively, often syncopated, short phrases that reflect the New. A parody mass is one in which the voice parts are based on a pre-existing sacred or secular song, with the polyphony created by multi-reworkings of the theme. The original motet has not survived but is thought to be derived from one of the Padilla’s own, as evidenced by techniques seen in other parody masses on his works. Certain memorable melodic phrases and harmonic sequences recur as motives, especially at the beginning and end of each movement, often with the counterpoint inverted or subtly transformed. Sometimes the voices combine in genuine eight-part writing; more often they are separated into two antiphonal choirs, exchanging short phrases in catchy speech-rhythms.</p>

<p>Listen for lush suspensions, expressive vocal writing and seamless polyphony in the Kyrie and Agnus Dei. The Gloria is characterised by accentuating crisp, dotted rhythms and an active dialogue between the two choirs. Padilla takes considerable liberties with the liturgical text, creating refrains that suggest the religious fervour of a gospel meeting and hint at the didactic, evangelising purpose of music in the colonial church – ‘Bonae voluntatis’ (goodwill) ‘Miserere nobis’ (have mercy upon us), ‘Credo’ (I believe) ‘Domine Deus sabbaoth’ (Lord God of hosts).</p>

<p>Felix Mendelssohn (1809-1847) was a German composer and conductor who was widely recognised as a musical prodigy. Essentially conservative in taste, he was responsible for the revival in interest of Bach’s works and was well-received throughout Europe. He wrote many smaller-scale sacred works for unaccompanied choir. Sechs Lieder, Op.59 remained unpublished until after the composer’s death. The subtitle, ‘im Freien zu singen’ (‘for singing outdoors’) indicates the Romantic spirit of reconnecting with nature and escaping the sweeping industrialization of the 19th century. Most of the songs are in simple strophic settings and straightforward homophonic textures, with the harmonic vocabulary drawn from the diatonic sonorities of the principal key, with chromaticisms in response to the text. Im Grünen (In nature) is a call to escape the stifling indoors and to seek emotional solace in nature. Frühzeitiger Frühling (Early spring) is joyfully of meadows, brooks, humming bees and the effervescent expectation of the arrival of the poet’s sweetheart. Abschied vom Walde (Farewell to the forest) is a hymn-like description of the singer’s need to move through life yet maintain an emotional connection with an emotional home. Die Nachtigall charms listeners and singers to reflect upon the simple, old songs of the nightingale. In Ruhetal (Valley of rest), the poet muses on the golden evening and sorrowfully wonders, in a poignantly chromatic moment, if his time has come. Jaglied (Hunting song) depicts hunters galloping through and out of a forest, in nervous anticipation and the exhilaration of anticipation of what might lie ahead.</p>

<p>Zoltán Kodály (1882-1967) was, along with Bartok, one of the creators of art music based on Hungarian folk sources, helping establish a high-level national musical culture. His development was profoundly influenced by his folksong experiences and by the embodiment of the Hungarian spirit. The evocative Matra Pictures, although written as a seamlessly fluid piece, is a compilation of five folksongs: Vidrócki’s hunting, The farewell, The message, Summertime and Stealing chickens, ordered to form a narrative thread. Kodály was a vocally-orientated composer for whom melody was of the highest importance. In 1966 he wrote ‘Our age of mechanisation leads along a road ending with man himself as a machine; only the spirit of singing can save us from this fate’.</p>

<p>The English madrigalist John Bennet (1675-c1614) published his first collection of madrigals in 1599 when in his early twenties. The delightful All creatures now is from The Triumphs of Oriana, a famous collection of 1601 commissioned by Morley in honour of Queen Elizabeth, and it is one of the most-loved of all madrigals. It is mostly homophonic, with a few obvious instances of word-painting: listen for an effervescent ‘merry’-ment, at the start, followed by hovering birds, and a stately elongation of the word ‘Long’ (live fair Oriana) towards the end of the piece. The six-part This sweet and merry month of May is one of very few of the compositions of William Byrd (1543-1623) that might rightly be called a madrigal. The piece begins with a brief canonic duet for two sopranos, with an upward flourish on ‘merry’ and gently arched quavers depicting birdsong. A brief section in triple meter sees homophonic groups of three, four, and five voices. The ‘beauteous Queen of second Troy’ – Queen Elizabeth and the British realm – is saluted in C major; the final line, ‘take well in worth a simple toy’, is a false modesty: the poet’s accomplished offering to a mighty monarch being presented as a mere trifle.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A summer garden concert celebrating the beauty of nature and the transient nature of life through choral music.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://cantandum.westminster.org.uk/assets/images/480686639_2541759206030368_918592212462190050_n.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://cantandum.westminster.org.uk/assets/images/480686639_2541759206030368_918592212462190050_n.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>