<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.2.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://cantandum.westminster.org.uk/programme-notes/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://cantandum.westminster.org.uk/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2025-07-21T13:03:13+00:00</updated><id>https://cantandum.westminster.org.uk/programme-notes/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Cantandum - London chamber choir | Programme</title><subtitle>Cantandum is a London-based chamber choir dedicated to performing a diverse repertoire of choral music, from Renaissance masterpieces to contemporary works. Join us for inspiring concerts, community events, and a celebration of vocal excellence.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">harps of heaven to hands of man</title><link href="https://cantandum.westminster.org.uk/programme-notes/hands-of-heaven/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="harps of heaven to hands of man" /><published>2025-03-21T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-03-21T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://cantandum.westminster.org.uk/programme-notes/hands-of-heaven</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://cantandum.westminster.org.uk/programme-notes/hands-of-heaven/"><![CDATA[<p>The renowned Westminster-based chamber choir Cantandum presents a concert of two exquisite meditations on the theme of the Crucifixion.</p>

<p>Finzi - Lo, the full final sacrifice
Buxtehude - Membra Jesu nostri</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A moving programme exploring the Crucifixion through masterworks by Finzi and Buxtehude.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://cantandum.westminster.org.uk/assets/images/484963813_1328266355033782_8405013237342222704_n.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://cantandum.westminster.org.uk/assets/images/484963813_1328266355033782_8405013237342222704_n.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">From Christmas to Candlemas - A Choral Journey</title><link href="https://cantandum.westminster.org.uk/programme-notes/from-christmas/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="From Christmas to Candlemas - A Choral Journey" /><published>2025-02-02T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-02-02T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://cantandum.westminster.org.uk/programme-notes/from-christmas</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://cantandum.westminster.org.uk/programme-notes/from-christmas/"><![CDATA[<p>The Westminster-based vocal consort Floreat takes us on a journey from the birth of Christ to the Presentation at the Temple 40 days later, celebrating the feasts that fall between the two.</p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Byrd</strong> – Vigilate (Advent)</li>
  <li><strong>Victoria</strong> – O magnum mysterium (Christmas)</li>
  <li><strong>Praetorius</strong> – Magnificat quinti toni, with Christmas interpolations</li>
  <li><strong>Tomkins</strong> – Stephen being full of the Holy Ghost (St Stephen, 26 December)</li>
  <li><strong>Philips</strong> – Iste est Joannes (St John, 27 December)</li>
  <li><strong>Coventry Carol</strong> (Holy Innocents, 28 December)</li>
  <li><strong>Hooper</strong> – Almighty God, which madest (Circumcision, 1 January)</li>
  <li><strong>Poulenc</strong> – Videntes stellam (Epiphany, 6 January)</li>
  <li><strong>Philips</strong> – Tu es vas electionis (Conversion of St Paul, 25 January)</li>
  <li><strong>Byrd</strong> – Senex populum portabat (Candlemas, 2 February)</li>
  <li><strong>Holst</strong> – Nunc dimittis (Candlemas)</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="floreat">FLOREAT</h2>
<p>Gilly French, Helen Prentice, Catharine Robertson, Robert Harvey Wood,
Jonathan Bull, Manvinder Rattan, Iain Butler, Willow Northeald
with Matthew Blaiden (organ)</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A choral programme tracing the journey from Christmas to Candlemas, featuring works by Byrd, Victoria, Praetorius, and others.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://cantandum.westminster.org.uk/assets/images/481915581_1316046386255779_5112616860334355451_n.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://cantandum.westminster.org.uk/assets/images/481915581_1316046386255779_5112616860334355451_n.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">The Silver Swan - a concert of endings and beginnings</title><link href="https://cantandum.westminster.org.uk/programme-notes/the-silver-swan/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Silver Swan - a concert of endings and beginnings" /><published>2024-11-14T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-11-14T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://cantandum.westminster.org.uk/programme-notes/the-silver-swan</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://cantandum.westminster.org.uk/programme-notes/the-silver-swan/"><![CDATA[<p>The Westminster-based chamber choir Cantandum, renowned for interesting programming and the quality of its vocal sound, presents a lovely programme on the theme of endings and beginnings.</p>

<ul>
  <li>Gibbons – The Silver Swan</li>
  <li>Lassus – Bonjour, mon coeur</li>
  <li>Greene – Lord, let me know mine end</li>
  <li>Gabrieli – Nunc dimittis à 14</li>
  <li>Howells – This is the little door</li>
  <li>Mendelssohn – Ave Maria</li>
  <li>Bainton – And I saw a new heaven</li>
  <li>Rheinberger – Requiem in D minor</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="cantandum">CANTANDUM</h2>
<p>Organ – Jonathan Dods
Conductor – Gilly French</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A concert exploring themes of endings and beginnings through choral masterpieces.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://cantandum.westminster.org.uk/assets/images/481669741_1312784369915314_6266755974426932048_n.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://cantandum.westminster.org.uk/assets/images/481669741_1312784369915314_6266755974426932048_n.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">With cheerful notes - celebratory music by Handel and Wilbye</title><link href="https://cantandum.westminster.org.uk/programme-notes/with-cheerful-notes/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="With cheerful notes - celebratory music by Handel and Wilbye" /><published>2024-06-14T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-06-14T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://cantandum.westminster.org.uk/programme-notes/with-cheerful-notes</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://cantandum.westminster.org.uk/programme-notes/with-cheerful-notes/"><![CDATA[<p>The Westminster chamber choir Cantandum, renowned for its fine choral sound, has its summer concert (with orchestra) in Ashburnham Garden, a lovely hidden venue nestling by Westminster Abbey, on Friday 14 June at 7.15pm</p>

<p>Handel - Chandos Anthem 9, O praise the Lord with one consent<br />
Wilbye - The Lady Oriana, Sweet Suffolk Owl 
Handel - Foundling Hospital Anthem<br />
Conducted by Gilly French</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A joyful concert featuring celebratory music by Handel and Wilbye, exploring themes of happiness and praise through choral masterpieces.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://cantandum.westminster.org.uk/assets/images/480362496_1306652057195212_3183760725951177492_n.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://cantandum.westminster.org.uk/assets/images/480362496_1306652057195212_3183760725951177492_n.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Renaissance Treasures</title><link href="https://cantandum.westminster.org.uk/programme-notes/renaissance-treasures/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Renaissance Treasures" /><published>2024-03-20T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-03-20T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://cantandum.westminster.org.uk/programme-notes/renaissance-treasures</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://cantandum.westminster.org.uk/programme-notes/renaissance-treasures/"><![CDATA[<ul>
  <li>Lobo Versa est in luctum</li>
  <li>Lassus Missa Bell’ Amfitrit altera</li>
  <li>Byrd Ne irascaris Domine</li>
  <li>Josquin Praeter rerum serium</li>
  <li>White Lamentations a5</li>
</ul>

<p>Alonso Lobo (1555-1617) was a Spanish composer of the late Renaissance, considered by Tomás Luis de Victoria as his equal. Lobo’s elegiac masterpiece Versa est in luctum was written in 1598 for the memorial service at Toledo Cathedral for Philip II of Spain. One of his most enduring works, it was published in his Liber primus missarum of 1602, headed ‘Ad exequias Philip. II Cathol. Regis Hisp.’. The text is an exquisite and evocative imagery of heavenly harps, organs and voices in songful mourning. Waves of entries roll over one another, drawing the ear into cycles of harmonic movement, before resolving redemptively in the major.</p>

<p>Orlande de Lassus (1532-1594) was a leading composer of the late Renaissance. Born in modern-day Belgium and working throughout Europe, he became one of the most prolific composers of his time. Around 60 masses have survived complete, and many of them are parody masses, using secular works as a melodic source.</p>

<p>The magnificent Missa Bell’ Amfitrit’ altera is based on a madrigal that has so far remained unidentified but may be Venetian, since Amphitrite was a sea-nymph.  It is a superb example of the composer’s polychoral style, which rather than being purely antiphonal prefers interplay between parts drawn from both choirs.  The Christe eleison and Benedictus reduce to the flowing counterpoint of four voices, heightening the impact of the return to eight voices, and the whole piece is in a shimmering major mode.</p>

<p>William Byrd (1539-1623) was the most noted and prolific English composer of his time.  He became Organist and Master of the Choristers at Lincoln Cathedral in 1563 before moving to the Chapel Royal in London in 1572. During the 1580s and 1590s Byrd’s Catholicism became the driving force for his music; he wrote and openly published motets and masses, almost certainly composed for small chapel gatherings.  The elaborate and penitential Ne irascaris, Domine, along with its seconda pars Civitas sancti tui, is one of Byrd’s masterpieces and one of his most forceful acts of protest against the persecution of English catholics. The setting is of verses from Isaiah 64.  The atmosphere is of quiet polyphonic contemplation, with the melody contained within the range of a fourth, before the stark homophony of ‘Sion deserta facta est’. The final phrase is a moving lament for Jerusalem – a metaphor for the catholic church in England – in which the poignant words ‘desolata est’ are heard over 50 times.</p>

<p>The magnificent, dark-hued Praeter rerum seriem, by Josquin (1450?-1521) takes the form of a succession of carefully worked motifs around a cantus firmus. For much of the piece the polyphony is presented antiphonally between the three upper voices, when the plainsong is in the soprano, and the three lower voices, when it is in the tenor. The second part of the motet is rather freer than the first, concealing the plainsong in a more consistently six-part texture, breaking into a lilting triple-time where the text makes final reference to the mystery of the Trinity, before returning to the duple time of ‘Mater ave’.</p>

<p>Robert White (1538-1574), arguably one the leading English composers of his time, was appointed organist and master of the choristers at Westminster Abbey in 1570. He and his wife and young family died in the plague only four years later.</p>

<p>The five-part Lamentations, consisting of two separate laments customarily sung together, are magnificent pieces of vocal architecture, with emotion in both halves drawn towards the concluding ‘Jerusalem, Jerusalem, convertere ad Dominum Deum tuum’.  The writing is restrained, reflecting the sombre nature of the texts of the prophet Jeremiah lamenting the downfall of Jerusalem.</p>

<p>The first four chapters of the Book of Lamentations are written as acrostics, with the first line of each verse corresponding to the 22 letters of the Hebrew alphabet, perhaps expressing a principle of completeness.  White sets verses 8-13 from the first book, following the convention of setting these letters (starting from the 8th, Heth) in poetically flowering music, rather like an illuminated capital letter at the outset of each verse.</p>

<p>It is one of several superb settings of that text composed during the 1560s, perhaps suggesting that not everybody was happy with the religious situation.  The Babylonians’ sacking of Jerusalem (the historical impetus for the Lamentations of Jeremiah) had become a metaphor for the plight of English Catholics over the ensuing decades.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A Floreat concert featuring treasures from the Renaissance period, showcasing the golden age of choral polyphony.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Your sweetest notes employ</title><link href="https://cantandum.westminster.org.uk/programme-notes/your-sweetest-notes-employ/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Your sweetest notes employ" /><published>2024-03-08T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-03-08T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://cantandum.westminster.org.uk/programme-notes/your-sweetest-notes-employ</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://cantandum.westminster.org.uk/programme-notes/your-sweetest-notes-employ/"><![CDATA[<ul>
  <li>Stanford: <em>Ye choirs of New Jerusalem</em></li>
  <li>Stanford: <em>How beauteous are the feet</em></li>
  <li>Mozart: <em>Great Mass in C minor, KV 427</em></li>
</ul>

<p>The Anglo-Irish Sir Charles Villiers Stanford (1852-1924) was organist at Trinity College Cambridge and one of the founding professors of the Royal College of Music, where he taught composition. He was influenced by the classical principles of the music of Johannes Brahms, and counted amongst his pupils Holst and Vaughan Williams.</p>

<p>Ye choirs of New Jerusalem, an anthem for Eastertide, dates from 1910. The text is taken from the hymn by St Fulbert of Chartres, translated by Robert Campbell, on the theme of Christ as the deliverer of the prisoners from hell.  Stanford’s anthem alternates between two contrasting thematic ideas, one in the major mode in a lilting triple metre (‘Ye choirs of New Jerusalem’), the other in the minor and in quadruple metre (‘Devouring depths of hell their prey’). The triple metre returns for the splendid final ‘Alleluia’.</p>

<p>This fine setting of How beauteous are their feet takes its text from four verses of Isaac Watts’s hymn. Stanford contrives a sophisticated variation form based on the opening melodic idea, with the polyphonic treatment of each repetition subtly varied.  In the fourth verse – ‘The Lord makes bare his arm’ – the tonic minor brings with it  a moment of gravitas, which is soon dispelled by the uplifting return of the major mode.</p>

<p>The monumental Mass in C minor, by Wolfgang Amadeus Mozart (1756-1791), is one of his greatest works.  Like his Requiem, it is magnificent but incomplete, in concept perhaps echoing something of the extraordinary proportions of Bach’s Mass in B minor.</p>

<p>Mozart began work on this Great Mass in the summer of 1782, around the time of his marriage to Constanze Weber and at a time when he was acquainting himself with Handel’s oratorios and Bach’s great fugues.  It was premiered in Salzburg in October 1783, presumably in a partially complete form, with Constanze as a soprano soloist.  The autograph manuscript contains the Kyrie and Gloria, the only movements that are fully complete, the first two verses of the Credo in short score, and a wind band score of the Sanctus which has survived only as a copyist’s manuscript.  The end of the Credo and the entire Agnus Dei are missing.  Despite all this, several convincing reconstructions have enabled the work to be performed today.</p>

<p>The work is sometimes described as a cantata mass, with alternating movements for four- and eight-part chorus, ensemble and soloists.  The work opens with an exquisite Kyrie, for soprano soloist and choir, which is followed by a rousing choral Gloria, embodying the pomp and solemnity associated with Salzburg tradition.  An Italianate coloratura Laudamus te is next. Domine Deus is a glorious pyrotechnical duet for two sopranos, after which there is a powerful 8-part Qui tollis, an Italianate trio Quoniam tu solus sanctus and a magnificently fugal Cum sancto spiritu.  The two movements of the creed are sharply contrasting – a lively Credo followed by an ethereal soprano aria Et incarnatus.  The 8-part Sanctus contains a splendidly fugal Osanna, which is partly repeated after an extended Benedictus, a serious exercise in worked counterpoint for four soloists.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A concert celebrating the beauty of sacred music with works that employ the sweetest notes of choral tradition.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://cantandum.westminster.org.uk/assets/images/476398645_1298944694632615_307762129408279843_n.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://cantandum.westminster.org.uk/assets/images/476398645_1298944694632615_307762129408279843_n.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Byrd’s the Word</title><link href="https://cantandum.westminster.org.uk/programme-notes/byrds-the-word/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Byrd’s the Word" /><published>2023-12-07T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-12-07T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://cantandum.westminster.org.uk/programme-notes/byrds-the-word</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://cantandum.westminster.org.uk/programme-notes/byrds-the-word/"><![CDATA[<ul>
  <li>Josquin – Praeter rerum serium</li>
  <li>Tallis – Videte miraculum</li>
  <li>Byrd – Laudibus in sanctis</li>
  <li>Byrd – Kyrie from Mass for Four Voices</li>
  <li>Byrd – Vigilate</li>
  <li>Byrd – Sanctus and Benedictus from Mass for Four Voices</li>
  <li>Byrd – O quam gloriosum</li>
  <li>Byrd – Agnus Dei from Mass for Four Voices</li>
  <li>Bach – Lobet den Herrn</li>
  <li>Janequin – Le chant des oyseaux</li>
  <li>Passereau – Il est bel et bon</li>
</ul>

<p>The magnificent Praeter rerum seriem, by Josquin (1450?-1521) takes the form of a succession of carefully worked motifs around the cantus firmus on which it is based. For much of the piece the polyphony is presented antiphonally between the three upper voices, when the chant is in the soprano, and the three lower voices, when it is in the tenor. The second part of the motet is rather freer than the first, concealing the plainchant in what has become a more consistently six-part texture, breaking into triple-time where the text makes final reference to the mystery of the Trinity, before returning to the duple time of ‘Mater ave’.</p>

<p>Videte miraculum is the Responsory at Candlemas. The chant on which Tallis (1505-1585) bases his polyphony comprises several sections, the full choir alternating with solo cantor. He leaves the solo sections as unadorned chant, implanting the choral sections of chant in a six-voice polyphonic texture. Listen for the opening point of imitation on ‘miraculum’—a dissonance, repeated at regular intervals by each entering voice to hypnotic effect, and for fleeting glimpses of major at ‘ad matrem’.</p>

<p>William Byrd (1539-1623), a pupil of Tallis, was the most prodigiously talented and prolific English composer of his time.  His earliest-known employment was as Organist and Master of the Choristers at Lincoln Cathedral.  In 1572 he took up a position at the Chapel Royal in London.  During the 1580s and 1590s Byrd’s Catholicism became the driving force for his music; he wrote and openly published motets and masses, almost certainly composed for small chapel gatherings.  Daringly, he openly published this music; unsurprisingly, it is deeply expressive.</p>

<p>The athletically ebullient Laudibus in sanctis, a paraphrase in Latin elegiac verse of Psalm 150, comes from his Cantiones Sacrae of 1591. It is full of madrigalianisms, involving rhythmic rhetoric, syncopation, melodic representations of the words, and a wonderful section in triple time as the poet dances before God.</p>

<p>The Mass for Four Voices, dating from 1592 or 1593, is the first and perhaps most personal of his three masses.  It retains some techniques from the distant past, such as blurring the boundaries between the tenor and alto parts, yet there are moments of intensity as well.  A central tenet of Elizabethan catholicism was its historical legitimacy, and Byrd makes an explicit homage in referencing, especially in the Sanctus, the pre-Reformation composer John Taverner’s ‘Mean’ Mass.  A plaintive Kyrie and a delicate Sanctus and Benedictus look towards an exquisite Agnus Dei.</p>

<p>Vigilate is notable for its madrigalian characteristics, such as sudden changes in declamatory style, the highlighting of individual words and short phrases, and overt illustrations of textual ideas in the music. The text, from Mark 13: 35–37, is presented from the perspective of Christ, warning his disciples of their inevitable deaths, which could come suddenly and without warning. This message might be read as a warning to English Catholics about the potential mortal danger from civil authorities, or as a metaphor about God coming suddenly in judgment.</p>

<p>O quam gloriosum and its second part, Benedictio et claritas are motets for the Feast of All Saints.  The first is derived from the Magnificat antiphon ‘O how glorious is the kingdom’, and the second from the service of None, ‘Blessing and glory and wisdom and thanksgiving and honour and power and might be unto our God for ever and ever’.  A choir of saints radiates assurance, gleaming with lucid major triads and an even, suffused light, and shows Byrd working at the height of his inspiration.</p>

<p>Lobet den Herrn, by J.S. Bach (1685-1750) is usually considered a motet but its independent continuo part leads some to believe that it may stem from an otherwise lost cantata. Its attribution to Bach is questionable. The text comes from Psalm 117:1-2. The opening text is a fugue starting with the sopranos and cascading its way down to the basses. Billowing roulades on the word ‘preiset ihn’ (praise Him) are followed by supple homophony, giving way to a gracious fugal passage. An infectious, dancing Alleluia concludes the motet.</p>

<p>Le chant des oyseaux is a chanson by Janequin (1485-1558), with birdsong brilliantly portrayed in fast rhythmic figures.  In its first part, the singers bid sleepy hearts awaken, for the god of love is calling on the first of May, and the birds will amaze you. The following three parts sequentially introduce the royal song thrush and blackbird, the nightingale, and the cuckoo, shifting between brief French descriptors and nonsense syllables and music that emulate each bird’s chirping song. The text contains fleeting references to drinking, adultery, and other unholy behaviour.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A Floreat concert celebrating the genius of William Byrd, one of England's greatest composers.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://cantandum.westminster.org.uk/assets/images/476004915_1296504828209935_4908642338181519064_n.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://cantandum.westminster.org.uk/assets/images/476004915_1296504828209935_4908642338181519064_n.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">From darkness to light</title><link href="https://cantandum.westminster.org.uk/programme-notes/from-darkness-to-light/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="From darkness to light" /><published>2023-11-30T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-11-30T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://cantandum.westminster.org.uk/programme-notes/from-darkness-to-light</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://cantandum.westminster.org.uk/programme-notes/from-darkness-to-light/"><![CDATA[<ul>
  <li>Ledger – Jesus Christ the Apple Tree</li>
  <li>Buxtehude – Magnificat</li>
  <li>Ledger – Adam lay y bounden</li>
  <li>Wilbye – Draw on, sweet night</li>
  <li>East – Hence stars, too dim of light</li>
  <li>Rutter – Dormi, Jesu</li>
  <li>Davies – O little town of Bethlehem</li>
  <li>Poulenc – Videntes stellam</li>
  <li>Handl – Ab Oriente venerunt magi</li>
  <li>Holst – Nunc dimittis</li>
  <li>Macmillan – O radiant dawn</li>
  <li>Wood – O thou the central orb</li>
  <li>Handel – Let the bright seraphim; Let their celestial concerts all unite</li>
</ul>

<p>Philip Ledger (1937-2012) was Director of Music of King’s College, Cambridge between 1974 and 1982, and a noted choral composer. Jesus Christ the Apple Tree is an 18th-century poem that first appeared in London’s Spiritual Magazine in August 1761. The text to Adam lay y bounden is thought to date from around 1400 and is a macaronic setting of the story of the Fall of Man, Adam being released from limbo by the death of Christ four thousand years later.  Ledger’s settings are refreshingly unostentatious in their simplicity and craftsmanship, demonstrating simple yet memorable melody and harmony in uncomplicated verse structures.</p>

<p>Dietrich Buxtehude (1637- 1707), organist at the Marienkirche at Lübeck, is unlikely to be the composer of this Magnificat, but the piece has been so long associated with him that the attribution has remained.  It is a delightful piece which obtains striking results by way of enduring lilting melodies, simple harmonies, frequent hemiolas and a clear sectional structure.</p>

<p>John Wilbye (1574-1638) was a prolific composer of English madrigals, with a style characterized by delicate voice-writing, acute sensitivity to text, a seriousness of approach and a subtlety of musical ideas.  Draw on, sweet night, possibly the greatest of all the English madrigals, displays a wistful melancholy and subtle alternation of major and minor modes.  Michael East (1580-1648) was a member of the choir of Ely Cathedral before moving to Lichfield as a lay clerk and choirmaster.  Hence stars, too dim of light is from ‘The Triumphs of Oriana’, a collection of madrigals by 23 composers, commissioned by Thomas Morley in honour of an ageing Queen Elizabeth and painting her as an eternally bountiful queen of a pastoral Arcadia.  After a brief homophonic statement there follow several lines of nimble imitation, particularly effective on the wordy ‘you dazzle but the sight, you teach to grope by night’.</p>

<p>John Rutter (1945- ) is an English choral composer, especially renowned for his effective and enduring settings of many Christmas carols.  Dormi Jesu sets an anonymous Latin text with its translation by Samuel Taylor Coleridge and is a tender lullaby.  It is a classic example of his style, with its final blues-esque chord being an notable touch.  O Little Town of Bethlehem is best known in its setting to the English folk melody, ‘The ploughboy’s dream’, as arranged by Vaughan Williams, but this 1913 version by Henry Walford Davies (1869-1941) has become a much-loved alternative. It begins with a solo soprano recitative, of text from the angel’s message to the shepherds in the Gospel of Luke, before moving into four hauntingly beautiful verses, the first of which is also a solo.</p>

<p>Francis Poulenc (1899-1963) is one of the supreme composers of French religious music, with a simple and direct style.  His choral music is unusually taxing, with strange key changes and awkward intervals all making for startlingly beautiful textures.  Despite its brevity, Videntes stellam, from Quatre motets pour le temps de Nöel, is an exquisite example of the composer at the height of his choral brilliance, brimming with freshness and clarity.  Ab oriente venerunt magi, by the Bohemian composer Jacob Handl (1550-1591), dates from 1586 and is a setting of the Magnificat Antiphon for Epiphany, telling the story of the Wise Men and their gifts of ‘aurum, thus et myrrham’.  It starts with lovely word-painting depicting the journey to Bethlehem and ends with a dance-like Alleluia.  The 8-part unaccompanied Nunc dimittis by Gustav Holst (1874-1934) was first performed liturgically on Easter Sunday 1915 and thereafter remained in manuscript form until 1979 when a published edition appeared, revised by the composer’s daughter Imogen.  Holst’s esteem of Byrd and Palestrina is especially evident in the modal and antiphonal writing of this glorious piece.</p>

<p>O Radiant Dawn is the antiphon for 21 December. The 2007 setting by James Macmillan (1959-) depicts a fervent longing for Christ, with suspensions and dynamic crescendos emphasising the increasing desperation of the people and the final resolution from dissonance to consonance maybe a representation of the conflicts resolved by Jesus’ coming.  The Irish composer Charles Wood (1886-1926) wrote a considerable amount of church music, mostly towards the end of his life.  O Thou, the central orb is skilfully crafted and a joy to sing. The ‘central orb’ is Jesus, bringing to us God’s eternal light; it also symbolises kingship and the piece is often sung at royal occasions.</p>

<p>Let the celestial concerts all unite is the jubilant finale to the oratorio Samson, by G.F. Handel (1685-1759).  The largest of his biblical oratorios, written shortly after Messiah, it was a triumphant success, not least because of the inspired last-minute addition of a dazzling soprano aria, Let the bright seraphim, composed for the renowned Italian singer Christina Avoglio who happened to be in London that season and was willing to make a cameo appearance in Handel’s new oratorio.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A concert exploring the journey from darkness to light through sacred choral music.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://cantandum.westminster.org.uk/assets/images/476099596_1296497311544020_6095055138450864273_n.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://cantandum.westminster.org.uk/assets/images/476099596_1296497311544020_6095055138450864273_n.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">And music shall untune the sky - Celebratory Odes by Handel and Purcell</title><link href="https://cantandum.westminster.org.uk/programme-notes/and-music-shall-untune-the-sky/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="And music shall untune the sky - Celebratory Odes by Handel and Purcell" /><published>2023-06-09T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-06-09T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://cantandum.westminster.org.uk/programme-notes/and-music-shall-untune-the-sky</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://cantandum.westminster.org.uk/programme-notes/and-music-shall-untune-the-sky/"><![CDATA[]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A garden concert featuring celebratory odes by Handel and Purcell, celebrating the power of music.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Carole magnus eras – Music for a Monarch</title><link href="https://cantandum.westminster.org.uk/programme-notes/carole-magnus-eras/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Carole magnus eras – Music for a Monarch" /><published>2023-05-11T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-05-11T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://cantandum.westminster.org.uk/programme-notes/carole-magnus-eras</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://cantandum.westminster.org.uk/programme-notes/carole-magnus-eras/"><![CDATA[]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A Floreat concert featuring music written for and in celebration of monarchs throughout history.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://cantandum.westminster.org.uk/assets/images/472694161_1276806933513058_7714879660423850118_n.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://cantandum.westminster.org.uk/assets/images/472694161_1276806933513058_7714879660423850118_n.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>