<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.2.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://cantandum.westminster.org.uk/programme-notes/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://cantandum.westminster.org.uk/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2025-07-19T08:29:25+00:00</updated><id>https://cantandum.westminster.org.uk/programme-notes/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Cantandum - London chamber choir | Programme</title><subtitle>Cantandum is a London-based chamber choir dedicated to performing a diverse repertoire of choral music, from Renaissance masterpieces to contemporary works. Join us for inspiring concerts, community events, and a celebration of vocal excellence.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Summer at St Margaret’s</title><link href="https://cantandum.westminster.org.uk/programme-notes/summer-margarets/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Summer at St Margaret’s" /><published>2016-06-09T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2016-06-09T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://cantandum.westminster.org.uk/programme-notes/summer-margarets</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://cantandum.westminster.org.uk/programme-notes/summer-margarets/"><![CDATA[]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Join us for a delightful summer concert at St Margaret's Westminster, featuring choral classics and seasonal favourites in a beautiful setting.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Sung Eucharist</title><link href="https://cantandum.westminster.org.uk/programme-notes/sung-eucharist/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Sung Eucharist" /><published>2016-05-04T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2016-05-04T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://cantandum.westminster.org.uk/programme-notes/sung-eucharist</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://cantandum.westminster.org.uk/programme-notes/sung-eucharist/"><![CDATA[]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Experience a beautiful Sung Eucharist at St John’s, Smith Square, featuring choral music and liturgy in a stunning historic venue. All are welcome.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Salvator mundi – music for Passiontide</title><link href="https://cantandum.westminster.org.uk/programme-notes/salvator-mundi-music-for-passiontide/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Salvator mundi – music for Passiontide" /><published>2016-03-18T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2016-03-18T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://cantandum.westminster.org.uk/programme-notes/salvator-mundi-music-for-passiontide</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://cantandum.westminster.org.uk/programme-notes/salvator-mundi-music-for-passiontide/"><![CDATA[<blockquote class="blockquoteCantandum">
  <p>Weelkes <em>Hosanna to the son of David</em><br />
Victoria <em>Eram quasi agnus; Caligaverunt oculi mei</em><br />
Tallis <em>Salvator mundi</em><br />
Bruckner <em>Christus factus est</em><br />
Sanders <em>The Reproaches</em><br />
Tomkins <em>My shepherd is the living Lord</em><br />
Byrd <em>Ave verum corpus</em><br />
Weelkes <em>When David heard that Absalon was slain</em><br />
Holst <em>Four songs for voice and violin</em><br />
Tchaikowsky <em>The Crown of Roses</em><br />
Rutter <em>Sans day carol</em></p>
</blockquote>

<p>The first half of tonight’s programme features music inspired by Holy Week, from Passion Sunday to Good Friday.  Thomas Weelkes (1576-1623) was an English composer and organist, whose output of mostly vocal music included madrigals as well as anthems and services.   He became organist of Winchester and Chichester cathedrals, although he was dismissed for using being drunk at the organ and using foul language during divine service.  Hosanna to the Son of David opens with a majestic six-voice SSATBB proclamation, with a sonorous lower register, moving seamlessly between homophonic and imitative passages. The text is a composite paraphrase of verses from the Gospels of Matthew and Luke, detailing Jesus’s triumphant entry into Jerusalem.</p>

<p>Tomás Luis de Victoria (1548-1611) was the greatest Spanish Renaissance composer and one of the leading figures of church music in the Europe of his day.  His output was entirely religious: masses and motets, settings of the Magnificat and Lamentations, as well as antiphons, responsories and hymns.  The Tenebrae Responsories were sung at the highly elaborate and dramatised night-time office of Tenebrae during Holy Week.  The texts, 18 in total, trace the story of the Passion and were adapted from the Gospels with fourth-century additions.  Eram quasi agnus (I was like an innocent lamb) is for Maundy Thursday whilst Caligaverunt oculi mei (my eyes become dim with weeping) is from the Good Friday settings.  They are raw and poignant settings, characterised by energy and vitality, with a mystical intensity and direct emotional appeal.</p>

<p>Thomas Tallis (1505-1585) comes from the period often described as the Golden Age, the height of the English Renaissance, which saw the flowering of poetry, music and literature under the reign of Queen Elizabeth I.  Salvator mundi, a setting of the antiphon for Matins on the feast of the Exaltation of the Cross, is the first of his two settings of the text. It begins imitatively, with soprano and alto 2 in canon at the octave, but quickly moves into a style which is freer and more expressive, with insistent pitch repetition at ‘auxiliare nobis’, an affecting pathos of the descending ‘te deprecamur’, and dissonant intervals creating a sense of magnificence and piquancy.</p>

<p>Of all nineteenth century Austrian composers Anton Bruckner (1824-1896) was the most religious, and his music for the Roman Catholic liturgy is amongst the finest of the last 150 years. The radical nature of his works is characterised by dissonances, modulations and roving harmonies, with enharmonic transformations representing redemption through faith. Christus factus est, to a text from Philippians 2:8-9, follows what has been described as ‘a striking parallel to Christ’s journey of obedience unto death’.</p>

<p>John Sanders (1935-2003) was Organist and Choirmaster at Gloucester Cathedral from 1967-1994.   The Reproaches are a setting in English of the sequence sung on Good Friday and alternate psalmic verses with spaciously harmonised antiphons.  The form and atmosphere take as a point of reference Allegri’s Miserere, with its use of plainsong contrasted with harmony in the verses, although the harmonies used perhaps have more in common with Gesualdo, which the composer suggested gives the music a sense of timelessness.</p>

<p>The music of the second half of the concert is reflective and relates to the theme of the first. Thomas Tomkins (1572-1656) studied with Byrd before becoming a Gentleman of the Chapel Royal and Master of the Choir at Worcester Cathedral.  His most noted collection of works, Musica Deo sacra, was published posthumously in 1668.  In My shepherd is the living Lord a single solo voice is given prominence for the first verse, while the second verse section is a duet, with intricate writing for the organ contrasting with the rhythmic simplicity of the voice lines.  Ave verum corpus is a text for the feast of Corpus Christi and the setting by William Byrd (1543-1623), one of his best-loved pieces, conveys the perfect mixture of awe and joy as well as the fervour and conviction of his own beliefs.  Weelkes’s setting of the short Absalom lament in the Second Book of Samuel highlights the deeply personal nature of King David’s public and private mourning for his dead son.</p>

<p>Four Songs for voice and violin, by Gustav Holst (1874-1934) is a deceptively simple setting of texts which the composer found in A Medieval Anthology, Being Lyrics and Other Short Poems, Chiefly Religious compiled by Mary Gertrude Segar in 1915. None of the four songs contains a key signature or time signature: Holst uses modes and simple structures to give the music a folk quality, and a free-flowing rhythm to impart the feeling of improvisation and to imitate the flowing quality of speech.  There are four movements: Jesu sweet, My soul has nought but fire and ice, I sing of a maiden and My leman is so true of love.</p>

<p>The Crown of Roses, from Chansons pour la jeunesse by Pyotr Tchaikovsky (1840 – 1893), is a simple and moving story about the childhood of Christ, which also foreshadows the Passion.  Originally entitled Legend, it was composed to a Russian translation of an English text and was later re-translated back to English by Geoffrey Dearmer.  The Sans Day Carol tells of the whole life of Christ rather than just his Nativity and is thus appropriate to other times in the liturgical year, especially Easter.  It is well known in this fluid and seemingly effortless version by John Rutter (b 1934), and is so called because the melody and first three verses were written down at St. Day in Cornwall.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Cantandum presents sacred music for Passiontide featuring works by Weelkes, Victoria, Tallis, Bruckner, Sanders and Tomkins at St Stephen's, Rochester Row.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://cantandum.westminster.org.uk/assets/images/screen-shot-2016-04-11-at-21-14-54.webp" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://cantandum.westminster.org.uk/assets/images/screen-shot-2016-04-11-at-21-14-54.webp" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Salvator mundi – music for Good Friday</title><link href="https://cantandum.westminster.org.uk/programme-notes/salvator-mundi-music-for-good-friday/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Salvator mundi – music for Good Friday" /><published>2016-03-06T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2016-03-06T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://cantandum.westminster.org.uk/programme-notes/salvator-mundi-music-for-good-friday</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://cantandum.westminster.org.uk/programme-notes/salvator-mundi-music-for-good-friday/"><![CDATA[]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Experience a moving programme of choral and instrumental music for Good Friday, featuring works that reflect on themes of redemption and hope.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Sung Eucharist 2016</title><link href="https://cantandum.westminster.org.uk/programme-notes/sung-eucharist-2016/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Sung Eucharist 2016" /><published>2016-01-06T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2016-01-06T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://cantandum.westminster.org.uk/programme-notes/sung-eucharist-2016</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://cantandum.westminster.org.uk/programme-notes/sung-eucharist-2016/"><![CDATA[]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Join us for the Sung Eucharist 2016 at St John’s, Smith Square. Experience beautiful choral music and a moving liturgical celebration together.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Choral Evensong january 2016</title><link href="https://cantandum.westminster.org.uk/programme-notes/choral-evensong-january-2016/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Choral Evensong january 2016" /><published>2016-01-04T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2016-01-04T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://cantandum.westminster.org.uk/programme-notes/choral-evensong-january-2016</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://cantandum.westminster.org.uk/programme-notes/choral-evensong-january-2016/"><![CDATA[]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A moving Choral Evensong service held at Westminster Abbey in January 2016, featuring traditional Anglican music and reflective liturgical readings.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">On Christmas night …</title><link href="https://cantandum.westminster.org.uk/programme-notes/on-christmas-night/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="On Christmas night …" /><published>2015-12-11T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2015-12-11T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://cantandum.westminster.org.uk/programme-notes/on-christmas-night</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://cantandum.westminster.org.uk/programme-notes/on-christmas-night/"><![CDATA[<blockquote class="blockquoteCantandum">
  <p>Foster: <em>Nativity</em><br />
Hassler: <em>Hodie Christus natus est</em><br />
Tallis: <em>Gloria</em> from <em>Missa Puer natus est nobis</em><br />
H. Praetorius: <em>Magnificat quinti toni</em> with Christmas interpolations<br />
Clemens non Papa: <em>Magi videntes stellam</em><br />
Britten: <em>A Ceremony of Carols</em><br />
Vaughan Williams: <em>Fantasia on Christmas Carols</em></p>
</blockquote>

<p>Peter Foster (b 1967) is a composer, choral conductor and teacher based in Oxford.  He was the winner of the Budleigh Carol Competition in 2014, and is currently Director of Music at Our Lady’s Abingdon.  John Donne’s La Corona is a circle of seven sonnets, telling of successive phases of the life of Christ.  Nativity was composed in 2013; this is the first performance of the SATB version.  The poem is concerned with the paradox of the Incarnation: the God who ‘fills all place’, yet who becomes weak and vulnerable.  The music therefore has moments of contained stillness, and moments which allow a much more confident mood to emerge.</p>

<p>Hans Leo Hassler (bapt. 1562–1612) was a German composer belonging to a family of musicians. He studied at St Mark’s Venice with Andrea Gabrieli, whose famous nephew Giovanni was a fellow student.  The magnificent motet Hodie Christus natus est is written for two 5-part choirs and dates from 1591. It is serene in character, demonstrating a particularly Venetian feature of changing of metre into triple time for the ‘Alleluia’ sections at the end of each main line of text.</p>

<p>Thomas Tallis (1505-85) was the most important English composer of his time.  His output encompasses early and late sixteenth-century English styles and his career reflects the religious upheaval and political change that affected church music of this period.  Throughout his service to four successive monarchs he managed to avoid religious controversy yet also composed to meet different royal demands.  His extraordinary seven-part Christmas mass, Missa Puer natus est nobis, written in the time of Queen Mary, is based on the plainchant introit for Christmas Day.  It is lavishly scored and leaves an impression of immense grandeur, with the steady progression of cantus firmus in the tenor line – with each note assigned a value based on its vowel in the original text – coupled with a magisterial seven-part texture throughout.</p>

<p>The music of the north-German composer Hieronymus Praetorius (1560-1629) bridges the gap between the stile antico and the stile moderno of the early baroque. The Magnificat quinti toni was very much intended as a Christmas piece: while his other eight-voice settings appear to form a set (comprising one setting for each of the eight church tones), this additional setting on the fifth tone was published in 1622 alongside arrangements of the popular carols Josef lieber, Josef mein and In dulci jubilo which share the same distinctive double-choir scoring. In addition instructions are provided that the carols be interspersed between the verses of the Magnificat (a tradition notably observed by Bach when he wrote his own well-known setting for Christmas 1723), highlighting the Christmas significance of the fifth tone.  The Magnificat is essentially polychoral in style and would almost certainly have been originally performed with continuo and instrumental accompaniment, making dramatic use of antiphony between the two choirs. Many of the motivic features of the plainsong tone are much in evidence in the polyphonic verses, along with some lively word painting to accompany some of the more dramatic phrases in the text.</p>

<p>The nickname “non Papa” seems to have been given to the Dutch composer Jacob Clemens (1510-1556) by his publisher as a joke, to distinguish him either from the poet Jacobus Papa, or from the recently deceased Pope Clement VII. In the generation following the death of Josquin Desprez, Clemens non Papa was one of the most prolific and well-published composers of both sacred and secular music, but rather little is known of his life.  The text of the four-part Magi videntes stellam comes from the Magnificat Antiphon at First Vespers at the Feast of the Epiphany.</p>

<p>On a voyage home from America in 1942 Benjamin Britten (1913 – 1976) wrote his Hymn to St Cecilia as well as ‘seven Christmas carols… to alleviate the boredom’.  These were the earliest version of the composer’s popular A Ceremony of Carols, written for treble voices and harp, which was premiered in 1943 by the women of the Fleet St Choir.  The idea for the carol sequence seems to have come from The English Galaxy of Shorter Poems and five of them appear in the finished piece.  In it he began to refine and diversify his command of English verse-setting: the use of single vocal lines and their canonic multiplication, and the radiant tone, give the cycle strength as well as a multitude of colourings.  The SATB arrangement, by Julius Harrison, was commissioned in 1955 by its publishers.</p>

<p>Ralph Vaughan Williams (1872-1958) was the most important English composer of his generation and a key figure in the 20th-century revival of English folk music, carols and Renaissance madrigals.  His outlook was human and social; he never forgot that music was for people; and he showed a reverential, almost religious feeling for genuinely popular traditions despite being a ‘cheerful agnostic’.  The Fantasia is founded on four traditional English carols: The truth sent from above (Herefordshire), Come all you worthy gentlemen (Somerset), On Christmas night (Sussex) and There is a fountain (Herefordshire; tune only).  It is full of life-affirming melodies that never lose their welcome with each re-use and transformation throughout the piece.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A festive concert featuring choral works by Foster, Hassler, Tallis, Praetorius, Clemens non Papa, Britten, and Vaughan Williams.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://cantandum.westminster.org.uk/assets/images/screen-shot-2016-04-11-at-21-21-02.webp" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://cantandum.westminster.org.uk/assets/images/screen-shot-2016-04-11-at-21-21-02.webp" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Summer music in the garden</title><link href="https://cantandum.westminster.org.uk/programme-notes/summer-music-in-the-garden/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Summer music in the garden" /><published>2015-06-12T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2015-06-12T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://cantandum.westminster.org.uk/programme-notes/summer-music-in-the-garden</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://cantandum.westminster.org.uk/programme-notes/summer-music-in-the-garden/"><![CDATA[<blockquote class="blockquoteCantandum">
  <p>G.F. Handel Chandos Anthem 10: The Lord is my light
F.J. Haydn: Missa Sancti Nicolai</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Handel’s eleven Chandos Anthems were written for James Brydges, the first Duke of Chandos, who made his fortune as Paymaster-General in Marlborough’s Wars and maintained a musical establishment in his household at Canons Park, Edgware.  Although the nature of Handel’s connection there is not entirely clear, the quantity of music composed for the Duke suggests that he was essentially a Composer-in-Residence in the period 1717-18.  It seems the resources there, initially at least, were modest: in many of the scores from the period both altos and violas are largely absent and the anthems have a delightful chamber music quality.  The Lord is my light, the 10th anthem, is set for SATB chorus and an orchestra of violins, bassi, organ and a single oboe; the alto chorus parts are low and might have been sung by tenors at the time.</p>

<p>As with the other anthems it is an extended, multi-movement work, opening with a brief two-part overture and followed by a leisurely succession of arias and choruses.  Too long for liturgical use, the anthems nevertheless achieved a measure of popularity in their day as concert and ceremonial pieces.  The Lord is my light is set to verses from the Prayer Book versions of Psalms 27, 18, 20, 34, 28, 29, 30 and 45 and contains some of the finest music of Handel’s first English decade, with striking solos and remarkably varied choruses, all full of inner vitality and textual imagery.  Of particular note is the composer’s depiction of quiet prayer – ‘One thing I have desired of the Lord’ – and the tempestuous oceans ‘It is the Lord that ruleth the sea’ as well as a nobly yet joyously affirmative final ‘Amen’.</p>

<p>Haydn’s St Nicolas Mass dates from 1772, and was probably written for the name-day of Prince Nikolaus von Esterházy (6 December).  The work belongs to a distinct type of mass – the missa pastorale, often associated with Advent – with simple melodies, lilting metres and a propensity for the upper parts to move in parallel thirds, depicting musical images of the pastoral nativity and of obesiance and with the aim to comfort rather than uplift.  The opening and closing movements are in 6/4, an unusual metre in the Classical period, and the key, G major, provides a gentle sonority.  It is scored for SATB soloists and choir, strings (though the viola only has two short sections with an independent part), oboes and horns.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Enjoy Handel’s Chandos Anthem 10 and Haydn’s Missa Sancti Nicolai in a summer garden setting, featuring chamber orchestra and choir.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Sung Eucharist</title><link href="https://cantandum.westminster.org.uk/programme-notes/sung-eucharist-may-2015/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Sung Eucharist" /><published>2015-05-06T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2015-05-06T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://cantandum.westminster.org.uk/programme-notes/sung-eucharist-may-2015</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://cantandum.westminster.org.uk/programme-notes/sung-eucharist-may-2015/"><![CDATA[]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Join us for a beautiful Sung Eucharist at St John's, Smith Square, featuring uplifting choral music and a welcoming atmosphere for all.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Music for Lent</title><link href="https://cantandum.westminster.org.uk/programme-notes/music-for-lent/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Music for Lent" /><published>2015-03-13T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2015-03-13T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://cantandum.westminster.org.uk/programme-notes/music-for-lent</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://cantandum.westminster.org.uk/programme-notes/music-for-lent/"><![CDATA[<blockquote class="blockquoteCantandum">
  <p>Victoria Tenebrae Responsories for Maundy Thursday<br />
Poulenc Timor et Tremor; Vinea mea electa<br />
Palestrina Stabat Mater<br />
Sanders Reproaches<br />
Bach Komm Jesu, komm</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Tomás Luis de Victoria (1548-1611) was the greatest Spanish Renaissance composer and one of the leading figures of church music.  After 21 years in Rome and his ordination in 1575, he became chaplain to the Dowager Empress Maria in Madrid; he remained at the royal convent of the Barefooted Nuns of St Clare, first as choirmaster and later as organist, until his death 24 years later.  His music ranks with the greatest masterpieces of the Renaissance, and is characterised by a mystical intensity and direct emotional appeal.  The Responsories, published in 1585, were sung at Tenebrae during Holy Week to texts, 18 in total, which trace the story of the Passion.  The six we hear tonight are those for Maundy Thursday.  They are raw and poignant settings of bleak texts and are characterised by energy, vitality and, at times, an almost unbearable sense of pain.  The music was written for liturgical performance and keeps strictly to the repeats prescribed by tradition: an opening section and a second section, both for four voices; a third section for fewer voices, and a repeat of the second section – ABCB.  The power of the music lies in the balance between words and setting. The mood is introverted and spiritually intense, with extreme simplicity and directness of style.</p>

<p>Quatre motets pour un temps de penitence, by Francis Poulenc (1899-1963) were the first pieces in the composer’s fully-recognisable a capella style.  Written for the hanteurs de Lyon, they were intended as concert pieces. From the opening of the first motet, Timor et tremor, to a text from psalms in the Vulgate of St Jerome, Poulenc builds his own dramatic but modest sound-world, with sharply-defined dynamic contrasts, an unsettled metre, and distinctive harmonic progressions depicting the ‘fear and trembling’ associated with the Crucifixion. This engrossing stylistic progression feels as if it is dictated by the text’s increasing intensity, driving towards the concluding ‘non confundar’ and a chromatically descending soprano line.  The second motet, Vinea mea electa, with a text from the third responsory for Matins on Good Friday, contrasts the tender opening, in sonorous six-part C sharp major, depicting loving references to the vine, through a shift to the modal tonic minor and a calm resignation at the impending Crucifixion, with anger at the possibility of Barrabas’ release.</p>

<p>Giovanni Pierluigi da Palestrina (1525-1594) was one of the towering figures of late sixteenth-century music and at the time of his death was considered by some to be the finest musician in the world.  He was primarily a prolific composer of masses and motets: the double-choir Stabat Mater, dating from about 1590, produces rich sonorities and an outstanding beauty of tone within the moderate compass of the voice parts.  It has been described as a ‘dramatic fresco in music, filled with light and shade’ and is an acknowledged masterpiece of Renaissance choral writing which, many would say, has never been surpassed.  The text is of 13th century origin, with a distinctive pattern of three-line verses each of 8, 8 and 7 syllables, and is a meditation on the suffering of Mary at the Crucifixion.</p>

<p>John Sanders (1935-2003) was Organist and Choirmaster at Gloucester Cathedral from 1967-1994.   The Reproaches are a setting in English of the sequence sung on Good Friday and alternate psalmic verses with spaciously harmonised antiphons.  The form and atmosphere take as a point of reference Allegri’s Miserere, with its use of plainsong contrasted with harmony in the verses, although the harmonies used perhaps have more in common with Gesualdo, which the composer suggested ‘gives the music a sense of timelessness’.</p>

<p>The music of Johann Sebastian Bach is revered for its technical command, artistic beauty and intellectual depth.  Now regarded as one of the greatest composers of all time, his work was not well-known until the 19th century.  Komm Jesu, komm, the fifth six motets, dates from around 1723-34 and is a setting of a funeral poem written by Paul Thymich (d. 1684).  The setting is for SATB double choir.  The opening section, in moderate triple metre, is the darkest.  Descending lines and angular counterpoint predominate, accentuating the hardships of life, with a sustained pedal tone for basses leading to a clear cadence. It is remarkable for its word-painting, notably at ‘Der saure Weg’ (the bitter way), where the bitterness of life is emphasised with a downward leap of a diminished seventh in every voice, perhaps implying that nobody is exempt from earthly trials. The mood shifts to a more hopeful sentiment which, in turn, moves into a stately expression of faith; the words ‘You are the right way, the truth and the life’ are set as a dance in 6/8 for alternating choirs, moving through an interval of a fifth each time and culminating in a true eight-voice polyphony. With ecstatic confidence, a stately four-part chorale concludes the motet with the words ‘My spirit…shall soar with its creator’.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A programme of choral masterpieces for Lent, featuring works by Victoria, Poulenc, Palestrina, Sanders, and Bach at St Stephen’s, Rochester Row.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://cantandum.westminster.org.uk/assets/images/screen-shot-2016-04-11-at-21-17-50.webp" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://cantandum.westminster.org.uk/assets/images/screen-shot-2016-04-11-at-21-17-50.webp" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>